¬
{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_AZTECS_DESCR}Difficulty: Estimated Very Hard \n\nThe Aztec Empire of the Triple Alliance dominates the heart of the New World. Made up of three separate tribes, the Aztec alliance acquires its name from the dominant Mexica tribe, known amongst the others as the ‘Aztecs’. The Alliance rules over many nearby city-states, enforcing tribute on pain of invasion and sacrifice.\n\nThe Aztecs primarily worship Huitzilopochtli, the god of war and the sun, who struggles constantly to hold back the darkness and requires nourishment in the form of human sacrifice. The Aztecs believe the world may end at the end of a 52 year cycle, which is quickly approaching, unless they can keep Huitzilopochtli strong. It is this need for sacrifices that drives the Aztecs to conquest. New territories mean new populations that can be used as slaves and, more importantly, sacrifices to stave off the end of the world.\n\nThe Aztecs have many enemies, and launching an invasion of the Old World from across the Atlantic will only multiply them. However, it seems unlikely that any one of them could overcome the mighty Aztec empire, and many Aztecs think the omens are but a test of their faith.\n\nThe Aztecs utilise many brave and fearsome warriors, including the Jaguar and Eagle orders. Their lack of cavalry is compensated by the overwhelming number of fierce warriors they can field.
{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_AZTECS_TITLE}The Aztec Empire
{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_BYZANTIUM_DESCR}Difficulty: Estimated Hard \n\nByzantium is essentially the Greek speaking remnants of the Eastern Roman Empire and the centre of Orthodox Christianity. The Byzantines themselves merely see their Empire as an unbroken continuance of the Roman Empire and its Emperors. The Empire is currently a shadow of its former self, having lost a great deal of territory in Asia Minor to the Seljuk Turks, and in other areas to internal strife and civil war. Current Emperor Manuel I is a dynamic leader and a resourceful general determined to build on the progress made by his immediate predecessors in restoring the Empire to its former glory. \n\nThe Byzantine Empire will need to regain its losses to the Turks in Asia Minor as well as the regions lost to internal strife, before it can expand into other faction’s territories. Fortunately the Seljuks, as well as the Egyptians, are more focussed on the Crusader States; but should they fall the Byzantines are unlikely to withstand a united Islamic offensive. As such, some cooperation with the Crusader States will be necessary for the Empire’s wellbeing. \n\nThe Byzantine Empire was created on the back of a strong military tradition, although much smaller than in the past, the Empire’s forces tend to be well trained and disciplined. The Empire’s forces consist of a wide range of unit types, from heavy cavalry to infantry, and many ranged units including the devastating Greek Flame Thrower. 
{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_BYZANTIUM_TITLE}The Byzantine Empire 
{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_JERUSALEM_DESCR}Difficulty: Estimated Medium \n\nThe Kingdom of Jerusalem, as a Crusader State, was founded at the end of the First Crusade in 1099. Incorporating the County of Tripoli and considered by many to be the jewel of the Crusader Kingdoms, Jerusalem is made up of Franks, native Christians, Jews, Orthodox Christians and Muslims. As a result, a certain degree of religious tolerance exists within Jerusalem, which is now ruled over by the Crusading Franks. \n\nThe Kingdom of Jerusalem is ruled by King Baldwin IV, also known as 'The Leper King', although partially crippled by Leprosy since childhood, Baldwin has proven to be a dynamic ruler and an astute general. However, Baldwin has a difficult time ahead as both the Turks, under Nur ad-Din, and the newly revitalised Egypt, under Salah al-Din, are intent on driving the European Infidels out of the Holy Lands. Maintaining and building alliances with Jerusalem’s northern Christian neighbours, the Principality of Antioch and the Byzantine Empire could prove to be a wise strategy in the face of the growing Muslim threat. \n\nThe Kingdom of Jerusalem relies heavily on the might of its various knights including the Knights of Jerusalem and the mighty Constable of Jerusalem and his guards. Bolstering Jerusalem’s forces are the powerful Knights Templar, who provide Jerusalem with a range of troops from its Order such as crossbowmen, sergeants, as well as the formidable Templar Knights, including the Marshall of the Templars himself.
{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_JERUSALEM_TITLE}Kingdom of Jerusalem
{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_ANTIOCH_DESCR}Difficulty: Estimated Hard \n\nBeing on the First Crusade’s route to Jerusalem, Antioch was conquered and made into the Principality of Antioch in 1098, one year before Jerusalem was conquered by the Crusaders. Incorporating the County of Edessa, the Principality of Antioch lies along the coast north of Jerusalem. However, due to a more united Seljuk presence, under Nur ad-Din, Antioch has lost much of its inland holdings. \n\nThe Prince of Antioch, Bohemund III, must defend his realm and reverse Antioch’s decline. A wise move would be to maintain their strong alliance with fellow Crusaders, the Kingdom of Jerusalem. Such alliances will make Antioch’s task of reclaiming its lost regions, as well as expanding, far easier. However, first and foremost Antioch must repel Nur ad-Din’s attempts to drive the Crusading Franks out of the Holy Lands. \n\nAntioch is renowned for its strong heavy infantry, such as the mighty Canons of the Holy Sepulchre, as well as its Armenian auxiliaries, recruited from neighbouring local Christians. Antioch can also rely on the Order of St. John, who, besides providing the impressive Hospitaller Knights, including the Marshall of the Hospitallers himself, is able to field other more mundane, but no less effective, units such as sergeants and crossbowmen.
{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_ANTIOCH_TITLE}Principality of Antioch
{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_IRELAND_DESCR}Difficulty: Estimated Medium \n\nEngland’s recent invasion of Ireland is still well under way. English lords have now divided up sections of their Irish conquest amongst themselves, each ruling his section mostly independently, as their King now focuses his attention on issues closer to home. \n\nThe Irish chieftains have determined their best chance of driving the English from their lands is to throw their support behind one man, fellow chieftain Brian O’Connor, who they have recently appointed King of Ireland.  As their English overlords are stretched thin in Ireland, and with increasing problems from France and the other factions in Britannia for the hated English, the Irish people ready themselves for conflict under the banner of their new King. They are confident that once they reclaim their own lands, they are more than capable of taking the fight to England and beyond. They will, however, need to be careful of the Scottish or Norwegians if they begin to expand successfully. Ulster is visible from the ScottishHighlands, and either of those factions may try to invade Ireland to give them more leverage in their own war.\n\nThe British Isles are populated by a morass of factions, each seeking to establish itself as the dominant one. If the Irish can reclaim their lands, and successfully play the factions against each other while taking key conquests, there is no reason why they should not rule over the "Irish Isles". 
{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_IRELAND_TITLE}Ireland
{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_NORWAY_DESCR}Difficulty: Estimated Hard \n\nNorway has used its considerable naval power to control Orkney Island for many decades now and has only recently shown interest in establishing a greater presence on the Scottish mainland. While King Haakon remains in Norway, dealing with issues at home, he has placed his son Magnus Haakonsson in charge of the war effort in Britannia. \n\nScotland is Norways first obvious target for expansion in Britannia. However, it should not be taken lightly. Scotland's Highlanders are skilled and fierce warriors, and can match the Norwegians in strength and ferocity. What's more, Scotland is a hard rugged land that may not provide much benefit to Norwegian coffers. It may also be in Norway's best interest to assault the east coast of England or conquering Ireland, although they should be careful not to have too many enemies at one time.\n\nScandinavia and the Baltic also present challenges and opportunities for the Norwegians. Denmark has dreams of assuming control of the region, and Norway is one of its main targets for conquest and annexation. If the Norwegian wars in Britannia go well, there is no reason why Norway cannot defeat the Danes and establish itself as a Northern power as well. The opposite scenario is equally viable; a unified Scandinavia will allow more armies of Norsemen to advance on the British Isles.\n\nWith this in mind, careful accolation of resouces will be required in the short term, as trying to fight distant and nearby wars simultaneously will spread the Norwegian treasury thin..
{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_NORWAY_TITLE}Kingdom of Norway
{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_DENMARK_DESCR}Difficulty: Estimated Medium \n\nKing Valdemar has presided over a renewal of the Kingdom of Denmark. In 1157, three claimants of the Danish throne, including himself, agreed to split Jutland and its other possessions among themselves to end the civil war they had fought for the throne for the greater part of ten years. This invariably fractured and weakened the entire area. However, treachery on the part of one of the claimants lead Valdemar to re-instigate hostilities, and this time he succeeded in capturing the remaining territory for himself, reunifying the Danish lands and healing the scars of the Danish Civil War.\n\nBecause of this focus on internal restoration, Denmark stands neutral to all nations at this time. However, the newly-arrived Teutonic Order may threaten the balance of power in the Baltic Sea should they begin to expand successfully. Denmark’s success lies in the conquest and unification of the northern regions of Scandinavia. These hostile lands will make for a strong northern front. The Kingdom of Norway, the only other major Scandinavian power, is far too concerned with its raids and wars in distant Britannia to mount any serious resistance to the Danes. Denmark’s enemies may try and attack by sea but the Baltic has been home to Denmark’s Viking ancestors for centuries. Dominance of the Baltic Sea is at the heart of any future success for Denmark, both militarily and economically.\n\nHaving just emerged from centuries of paganism, Denmark still holds to Viking military traditions. They strive for death in battle and love the smell of salt in the air and the feeling of sea spray on their skin. The Danes brandish the two-handed axe like no other and take pride in the knowledge that no defence can withstand their attack. Fast ships carrying ferocious warriors will ensure that any nation residing on Baltic shores must always watch their back, for the Danes still carry the bloodlust of sea-raiding and village-sacking that filled their boyhood dreams.
{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_DENMARK_TITLE}Kingdom of Denmark
{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_TEUTONIC_ORDER_DESCR}Difficulty: Estimated Very Hard \n\nThe Teutonic Order was formed in the Holy Land from groups of German knights seeking to found their own crusading order. However, the Templar and Hospitaller orders were more established in Outremer, so the Teutonic knights began looking elsewhere to drive back the infidels from Christendom. They found it on the shores of the Baltic Sea, having been given a task to purge the last den of European paganism: Lithuania. The fact that the Order will conquer Lithuanian lands in the process is a happy secondary effect.\n\nPoland invited the Teutonic Order to the region, and is supportive of their actions at this point. However, some in the Polish court whisper that the Teutonic Knights are not to be trusted. The Orthodox people of Novgorod, wary of the Order's intentions, stand ready to defend against any attempt on their wealthy city and its trade routes. Denmark remains neutral, but grows wary of the Order’s new presence in the Baltic and watchful of their interest in trade. The Holy Roman Empire watches the Order’s actions like a proud parent, but the knights aim to forge their own great empire.\n\nIt is the pagans of Lithuania, however, that will feel the full force of the Order’s zeal and the sting of their swords. While the crusades rage in the distant Holy Land, many Europeans find that battling pagans is just as redemptive as slaughtering Muslims, and many flock to the Order's banner from all over Europe.\n\nThe Order’s might comes from its knights, whose skills are unmatched by any in these lands. However, men of this quality are in short measure and must not fall at the hand of a peasant’s crossbow. The quality troops of the Order will be urgently necessary in the short term. Having only recently arrived in the area, the Teutonic Order is surrounded in a hostile environment, and they face an uphill struggle to Christianize Lithuania and establish themselves as the Lords of the Baltic.
{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_TEUTONIC_ORDER_TITLE}The Teutonic Order
{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_EGYPT_DESCR}Difficulty: Estimated Medium \n\nUntil recently Egypt had been the centre of the Fatmid Empire, however Egypt’s former rulers grew weak and were eventually deposed by a cunning Kurdish general by the name of Salah al-Din. Originally sent by his master, Nur ad-Din, to govern Egypt in his name, the ambitious Salah al-Din soon set about creating his own powerbase on the Nile. \n\nWith its new ruler at the helm, Egypt grows from strength to strength. Salah al-Din has revitalised Egypt’s military and economy making Egypt the growing power in the Middle East. It seems inevitable that Salah al-Din will have to face the wrath of his former master in the north sooner or later. The winner of that struggle will in effect inherit the strongest Muslim empire in western Syria as well as the duty of defending the western Islamic world from the Frankish Crusaders. \n\nEgypt must defeat Nur ad- Din as soon as possible to avoid fighting both the Crusaders and Nur ad-Din at the same time. Alternatively an alliance with the Turks would also have the Crusaders facing a united Muslim front whilst allowing Egypt to expand westward and northwards in peace for a short while. The time has come for the Islamic redemption from the humiliating loss of Jerusalem almost a century ago.
{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_EGYPT_TITLE}Ayyubid Dynasty
{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_ENGLAND_DESCR}Difficulty: Estimated Hard \n\nThe decisive leadership of past Kings and nobles, as well as the powerful forces under its command, has won England control over much of the British Isles.  The price of their successful expansion however, is the resistance which now grows amongst the people they have subjugated.\n\nMany Welsh people living under English rule are becoming increasingly insubordinate.  Self-declared King of Wales, Llywelyn, who is also leader of the organized Welsh resistance, is a man the English would surely like to deliver a quick death to, in the hopes of quashing his rebellion before it gains further momentum.  Should the situation erupt into all out war, the Welsh mastery of the Longbow will be something of a concern for the English as they will need to counter its range and power with plenty of heavy infantry. \n\nAcross the Irish Sea, Brian O’Connor, the man recently elected King of Ireland by his fellow chieftains, has emerged as a serious threat to the tenuous English holdings in Ireland. With the Irish armies beginning to gather, and the population of the English-held cities there becoming more rebellious, the situation in the Emerald Isle is dire indeed for England.\n\nTo the north,  Scotland remains a considerable power, one which is currently able to cause England the most damage should they choose to attack.The Scottish people, however, have their hands full dealing with Norwegian Vikings. These same Vikings are of little immediate concern to England, that is however unless they attempt to recreate the journey their ancestors once took and look to recapture York. Should they decide to invade, they will find the English people are much more organised and powerful than they used to be. \n\nThe English must also carefully guard their holdings on the European mainland as well. The lords of France have begun to try and reinforce their claims to lordship over the English provinces of Normandy and Brittany, and are mobilizing their forces. Fortunately, England's alliance with the Flemish will mitigate that danger somewhat. Dangers and opportunities surround the English people, and only a strong king will be able to lead them to glory.
{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_ENGLAND_TITLE}Kingdom of England
{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_FRANCE_DESCR}Difficulty: Estimated Easy \n\nFrance is a shining example of feudalism in its rawest, and arguably, most delicate form. The French lords eagerly embrace the system that splits the country up into smaller provinces, duchies and fiefdoms, actively building up their forces to ensure their own security and power. Thanks to the strong force of will of the current king, Philip II Augustus, the French lords have finally found some semblence of unity.\n\nThis unity will be tested as France is surrounded by powerful rivals. The Holy Roman Empire to the east will look to establish control of French holdings. The Castilians, Milanese, and maybe even the papacy might also try to take the southern provinces. \n\nThe most pressing concern, however, is with the English. The English, (descendants of the Normans, the feudal vassals of France!) have established a strong kingdom in Britannia and hold the entire northern coastline of France. Perhaps the time has come for the French king to remind the English king of his feudal place through taking those lands back. England is beset by many factions in Britannia, and will be hard pressed to hold back a concentrated French effort to reclaim Normandy and Brittany. England's alliance with the County of Flanders, another rebellious vassal of France, will make this campaign difficult, but necessary.\n\nFurther consideration for King Philip must concern the state of the Holy Land. Pope Urban II had called for the First Crusade from the heart of France, and Frenchmen made up the bulk of the First Crusade's armies. The current Pontiff may call for another crusade soon to aid the beleaguered Crusader States, and will expect France to give as much as she did the first time.\n\nThe rebirth of the glorious empire of Charlemagne is possible, if the French can channel their national might correctly.
{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_FRANCE_TITLE}Kingdom of France
{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_HRE_DESCR}Difficulty: Estimated Hard \n\nThe Holy Roman Empire is a particularly misleading name for Europe's largest collective of kingdoms and fiefdoms, regardless which way one looks at it. For starters, it is the Byzantine Empire that truly carries on the legacy of the ancient Romans, and the notion that the Kaiser (the Germanic name for "Emperor") truly serves the Pope is quite laughable.\n\nThe current Emperor, Friedrich I, also known as "Barbarossa" due to his flaming red hair and beard, has shown himself to be the most politically powerful European crowned head at present. His grasp of military command, personal chivalrous character and ability to rally the German elector counts to him has led to a time of great power and prosperity for the Holy Roman Empire. He has also expressed an interest in crusading. His political and military power, however, has not endeared the Empire to the rest of Europe. It is distrust born of fear and jealousy, no doubt.\n\nHowever powerful and unified the Empire is at present, however, it is but a shadow of its glory in centuries past. It is a far cry from the days of Charlemagne when all of Western Europe answered to the Emperor. Now France is a separate entity, Italy has become a formidable group of city states (which Friedrich has tried and failed to bring to heel), the Danes block the route into Scandinavia and the kingdoms to the east are more of a threat than a place to lay claim to. The balance of power in the east may yet shift, however, thanks to the new presence of the German Teutonic Order of knights, who view themselves as children of the Holy Roman Empire.\n\nShould the Kaiser successfully defend the German heartland and muster the armies necessary for expansion, there seems no reason the Reich cannot expand into something to rival the first Roman Empire... Though this time it won't be a simple matter of bettering the barbarians.
{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_HRE_TITLE}The Holy Roman Empire
{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_LITHUANIA_DESCR}Difficulty: Estimated Medium \n\nLabelled as heathens by their neighbours, the Balts are some of the last remaining pagan worshippers in the region. Under the leadership of the great Mindaugas, they have been compelled to unify under the banner of the Kingdom of Lithuania. The new Kingdom achieved some early military success and earned respect as a true nation of the region. The gods have been with them so far, bringing hope that their culture and beliefs will continue to prosper through many Lithuanian generations.\n\nLithuania was once content to live in peace with its neighbors, with the occasional raid into Poland or the lands of the Rus' for slaves and sacrificial victims. However, the arrival of a German group of religious knights, the Teutonic Order, has seen the time of peace come to an end. The knights have arrived at the behest of the Poles, and the Order seeks nothing less than either the Christianization or extermination of the Lithuanians. While the knights may only control the small area of Prussia, the quality of their troops is something that the Lithuanians must be cautious about. By working to maintain peace with their other neighbours and through clever diplomacy, they may be able to form an alliance to destroy the Teutonic Order, should they become too powerful.\n\nLithuania can draw much strength by holding to the old ways. Following the pagan Gods of Perkunas, Giltine, and Dievas will unleash religious warriors that instil fear in the hearts of all men. However, if the Teutonic Order were to succeed in capturing many territories of Lithuania, and the Lithuanians were to become surrounded by Christian armies on all sides, they may be forced to change their ways to avoid death, enslavement, or exile at the hands of the Christians. Choosing the right time to convert from paganism to Christianity will be central to Lithuania’s survival in such a situation. Gods willing, may that day never come.\n\nLithuania’s strength in battle lies in its light cavalry and religious zealots, though both are lightly armoured and must use the cover of thick woods or skirmishing tactics. Surprise and speed will be Lithuania’s greatest assets, making good use of the open plains and thick woods prevalent in their home lands. Lithuania must use surprise and guerrilla tactics to weaken the heavier armies of their opponents, and then disappear as they had come – like ghosts.
{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_LITHUANIA_TITLE}Lithuania
{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_HUNGARY_DESCR}Difficulty: Estimated Hard \n\nA century after the final Christianization of Hungary from its pagan roots, the Hungarian people find that they are to be Catholicism's defender in the Balkan region. The most obvious threat to Hungary at the present is the Byzantine Empire. The Byzantines are trying to unify the southern Slavic lands as a buffer against any possible Latin attacks on Constantinople as well as to spread Orthodox Christianity, which is under threat from the invading Islamic Turks from the east. The Hungarians are Catholic and incorporate many Slavs in their kingdom, and so have a rallying cry to gather the various fractious Slavic kingdoms and chiefdoms to its banner. Regardless of the outcome, the Balkans will not know peace for many years.\n\nThe West is not a tempting direction for expansion, but there is opportunity there as well. The Holy Roman Empire is curretly strong and unified under Feidrich I "Barbarossa" and will make a dangerous enemy. The Venetian holdings in Dalmatia can be considered vulnerable, and will allow Hungary access to the Mediterranean. If they can also simultaneously hold their ports on the Black Sea, this will allow them to become a naval power. \n\nTo the North, the Baltic region is about to be set ablaze by the war between the nascent Teutonic Order and Lithuania. In all the unfolding chaos, Hungary may be able to find expansion as well. The Kievan Rus', an otherwise mighty adversary, will be focusing on their problems with the Teutonic Order and the arriving Mongol Hordes from the East. Hungary may yet be able to take Kiev and liberate the Ukraine's Catholic population.\n\nRegardless what Hungary's first move is, nothing will change the fact that it has the potential to achieve great glory, yet at the cost of even greater bloodshed.
{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_HUNGARY_TITLE}Kingdom of Hungary
{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_MILAN_DESCR}Difficulty: Estimated Hard \n\nMilan is one of the wealthiest and most powerful of the Italian city-states. Its strategic importance, independent spirit and great wealth have made it a tempting target for conquest throughout much of its history, most recently by the current Holy Roman Emperor- Friedrich I "Barbarossa", who claimed ownership over all of northern Italy by right of his being Holy Roman Emperor. Milan and the Italian city-states rejected Barbarossa's authority, and in retaliation he came across the Alps with a massive German army, besieging and laying waste to most of Milan in 1162.\n\nFive years after Milan was sacked, the rest of the Italian city-states formed the Lombard League, an alliance of mutual defense, under the leadership of Milan and Venice.The Lombard League went on to inflict a humiliating defeat of Barbarossa and his army at Legnano in 1176, only four years ago. The Germans retreated to Bologna, and the Lombard League members have won their freedom...for now. For their leadership in the Lombard League, Milan now commands the loyalty of many of the League members, most notably Genoa and Turin, with the notable exceptions of Florence and Venice. Florence has maintained its independence from outside influence, and the old rivalry between Milan and Venice has once again flared now that the Germans have been momentarily dealt with. \n\nThe Milanese are surrounded by possible allies and enemies. The Alps provide Milan with a natural barrier to the north that ensures the city is relatively safe from Swabia and the Holy Roman Empire - If the Milanese hold the mountain passes, they can hold off Northern Europe. While the mountains fence Milan off from the world, Genoa serves as the coastal gateway to the Mediterranean and beyond. One possible source of concern should come from Rome. The Pope was not pleased that the Milanese had overthrown the rule of the Archbishop of Milan a century ago, and he might try to re-instate clerical rule in a more...direct...fashion.
{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_MILAN_TITLE}Milan
{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_MONGOLS_DESCR}Difficulty: Estimated Medium \n\nAfter the complete defeat of the Khwarezmid Empire the Mongol army was split into two component forces. Genghis Khan led a division on a raid through Afghanistan and nothern India, while another contingent marched through the Caucasus and into Russia. As Genghis Khan gathered his forces in Persia and Armenia to return to the Mongolian steppes, the second force of 20,000 troops, commanded by generals Jebe and Subutai, pushed deep into Armenia and Azerbaijan. The Mongols destroyed Georgia, sacked the Genoese trade fortress of Caffa in the Crimea, and overwintered near the Black Sea.\n\nHeading Home, Subutai's forces attacked the Kipchaks and were intercepted by the allied but poorly coordinated troops of Mstislav the Bold of Halych and Mstislav III of Kiev, along with 80,000 Kievan Rus' to stop their actions. Subutai sent emissaries to the Slavic princes calling for a separate peace, but the emissaries were executed. At the Battle of Kalka River, Subutai's forces defeated the larger Kievan force, while losing the battle of Samara bend against the neighboring Volga Bulgars.\n\nUnder Genghis Khan's grandson Batu and the Golden Horde, the Mongols returned to definitively conquer Volga Bulgaria and Kievan Rus in 1237, Concluding the campaign in 1240.
{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_MONGOLS_TITLE}The Mongols
{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_MOORS_DESCR}Difficulty: Estimated Hard \n\nThe Moors were originally a nomadic people, the original inhabitants of Mauretania on the north coast of Africa. They rose from obscurity in the 8th century when they converted to Islam, and proceeded to spread rapidly in several directions - including north-west into the Iberian peninsula. They soon had almost total dominion over all of Iberia with the exception of the lands to the north where some resilient Christians held fast, but Islamic Spain was a collection of cities more than a true caliphate - until relatively recently.\n\nThe Almoravid Berbers were the first to unify al-Andalus (Islamic Spain) into a coherent Caliphate. However, the Almoravids grew weak and complacent in cultural refinement, and began losing ground to the newly revitalized Christian Iberian kingdoms of Leon, Castile, Aragon and Portugal and their "Reconquista". \n\nThe Almohad sect of the Moors, a more ascetic Islamic, militaristic and uncompromising sect than their Almoravid precursors, have recently taken total control of the Moorish holdings stretching from Cordova to Cyrenacea, and aim to crush Christianity in al-Andalus once and for all. They currently control more territory in Iberia than any other major power, but must be careful about the possiblity of an alliance between the Christian kingdoms. It may be possible for a wise caliph to play the Iberian Christian factions against each other, but they must also be careful about wanton expansion as well. The crusades that devastated their Islamic brethren in the Holy Land may just as well be directed against them. \n\nStill, the Almohads view themselves as the cutting edge of the Scimitar of Islam against Christendom. Possibilities for expansion against the infidel are ripe, whether in Iberia or across the Mediterranean. By the same token, Christian attacks can come in any direction as well. The Almohads will have to find strength in their faith to face these myriad threats for the glory and expansion of Islam.
{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_MOORS_TITLE}Moorish Caliphate
{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_PAPAL_STATES_DESCR}Difficulty: Estimated Hard \n\nThe Papal States stand at the heart of Christendom, yet are surrounded by ambition, rivalry, and constant intrigue. Though the Pope wields immense spiritual authority as the Vicar of Christ, his temporal power is fragile, contested by the Holy Roman Empire to the north, the Kingdom of Sicily to the south, and ambitious Italian city-states seeking independence. To defend the Church, the Papacy must balance diplomacy, faith, and arms in a fractured Italy.\n\nThroughout the 12th and 13th centuries, the Papacy struggled to assert its supremacy over secular rulers. Emperors such as Frederick Barbarossa and Frederick II challenged papal authority, leading to prolonged conflicts that ravaged central Italy. Internally, rival noble families and rebellious communes threatened stability, while externally the Pope sought to direct Christendom through crusades, excommunications, and alliances.\n\nAs the spiritual leader of Western Christendom, the Pope must defend Rome, maintain unity among Christian kingdoms, and guide the faithful against heresy and infidel powers. Survival depends not on sheer military might, but on shrewd diplomacy, careful use of influence, and the ability to turn faith into a weapon stronger than steel.
{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_PAPAL_STATES_TITLE}The Papal States
{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_POLAND_DESCR}Difficulty: Estimated Hard \n\nThe late king Boleslaw III Wrymouth unified Poland from numerous small duchies, only to divide it on his death bed among his five sons, with the institution of a complex system of seniority in deciding who will get to the become the next Polish Grand Duke and de facto ruler of the realm. This system has been in place for a few decades now, but it has led to internecine power struggles amongst the descendents of Boleslaw, and the grip of any Grand Duke is tenuous at best.\n\nWith this internal squabbling among the Poles, the pagan Lithuanians were allowed to grow powerful in the northern Baltic forests, and began to mount a serious threat to the already weakening Polish realm. In response, the Polish Grand Duke has invited a new German military order, the Teutonic Knights, to the Baltic to help cull the numbers of the Lithuanians and help spread Christianity in the last den of European paganism. The German knights were happy to accept.\n\nThe knights recently landed on the shores of pagan Prussia to Poland's north with a large force of extremely disciplined and professional troops, and proceeded to convert and/or kill the native Prussian population with a gusto that many in Krakow saw as particularly alarming. After they had established control of Prussia, the Teutonic Order set itself up as a feudal monastic state on a much grander scale than had ever been attempted before, and is even now beginning to fight an open war against Lithuania in earnest. The Poles, while officially supportive of the knights' work, are beginning to think that they got more than they bargained for with the Teutonic Order. God only knows what impact the knights will have on the entire Baltic region. \n\nAlthough Poland’s military is not the strongest in any one area, it has strength in diversity. The Polish military can hold its own in the open fields with fast cavalry, defend cities with heavy infantry, and has all of the modern technology found in Christian Europe. Poland will always have a chance for success by attuning their army to the weaknesses of their enemies.
{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_POLAND_TITLE}Poland
{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_PORTUGAL_DESCR}Difficulty: Estimated Medium \n\nOf all of the European royal courts, Portugal is the youngest, having only just recently been recognized by the pope as an official kingdom. While Portugal has maintained its independence from Castilian rule for over a century, it was regarded mostly as a rebellious county which happened to resist Castilian occupation very well. The recent papal decree has allowed the Portuguese to breathe a collective sigh of relief, but most believe that King Alfonso of Castile and Leon will ignore the Pontiff and try to conquer them anyway. However, Castile is the least of King Afonso's worries now.\n\nDespite some of the Kings and Emirs of the Iberian Peninsula supporting religious tolerance, the Christian and Islamic faiths do not appear to be able to share these lands peacefully. The ongoing Reconquista ensures that the Moors will be an enemy of Portugal, at least until they are driven back across the straits of Gibraltar. That said, even then they will still be an immediate threat.\n\n With lingering threats from both Christian and Islamic kingdoms in Iberia, Portugal's future is still far from ceratin. \n\nSome of the Portuguese believe that the best tyranny to face is that of distance. Poised on the edge of the civilised world, perhaps Portugal's fortunes lie across the seas and oceans, rather than across her immediate borders. A unified Iberia under Portugal, however, will allow the former rebellious county to rise to amazing heights, and conquer an empire.
{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_PORTUGAL_TITLE}Kingdom of Portugal
{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_RUSSIA_DESCR}Difficulty: Estimated Very Hard \n\nThe Kievan Rus' control the single largest kingdom in Europe. Masters of the trackless steppes, their armies and trading caravans range from the borders of mighty, cosmopolitan Novgorod on the Baltic Sea to the shining city of Kiev, their capital, on the Black Sea. As one of the Orthodox Christian powers, they enjoy a healthy alliance with the powerful and wealthy Byzantine Empire to the south. The Russian armies are large, mobile and varied, and ideal for fighting on the open steppes that comprise their homelands. No other power would dare to think of challenging the will of the Grand Princes of Kiev...until now.\n\nNovgorod, once the capital of the Rus' was able to break free of the influence of the Kievan Princes, and have set themselves up as a mercantile republic. Although trade between the Kievans and their new northern neighbor will bring wealth, the lands occupied by Novgorod belong to the Kievan Grand Princes by ancient right. Perhaps one day the Kievan Rus' can unify all of their former lands, but now is not the time to entertain such fantasies. War is on the doorstep of Kiev, and they will need all the friends it can find, even with its large and powerful armies.\n\n Novgorod is about to be caught in a bloody war in the Baltic as a German crusading order, the Teutonic Knights, seeks to wipe out pagan Lithuania. The fanatical warrior monks may also lash out at any who deny the authority of the Pope, Orthodox Christians included. It may be best to ally with Novgorod and see these invaders from the Baltic, although this may antagonize the kingdoms of Poland and Hungary. This is the age of crusades, and an "armed pilgrimage" from Christendom to the gates of Kiev would be most unwelcome.\n\nEven worse developments are appearing in the east. Refugees have begun flooding into the eastern outposts of the kingdom, spinning horrible tales of a race of demons who crawled from the depths of Hell in central Asia and began a terrible conquest of world. These men, they say, called the "Mongols" are half-man and half-horse, and fight in a manner that is totally devoid of mercy. While many courtiers in Kiev think these to be nothing more than fanciful tales, many of the easternmost Russian outposts are falling silent. Perhaps these stories may not be so fanciful after all. If they are true, than the Rus' will need to muster every last man in order to defend itself against this new threat.
{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_RUSSIA_TITLE}Kievan Rus
{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_NOVGOROD_DESCR}Difficulty: Estimated Hard \n\nThe great city of Novgorod is treasured by its people, as it is considered an important hub for trade and a conduit between the Baltic Sea and Byzantium. Whoever controls Novgorod has control of the trade in the region, which, in these troubled times, means power.\n\nNow is the time of the mighty Prince Alexander Nevsky. Alexander led Novgorod to intoxicating victories against the Swedes at the river Neva and against the Teutonic Order at Lake Chudskoe. However, he knows that the Western Tartar army lies to the east and that expanding west may cost them their homelands and possibly the loss of the great city itself.\n\nNovgorod will never forget the atrocities the Teutonic Order brought to their homelands, but they present a face of neutrality for the sake of trade in the region. Choosing their enemies carefully and remaining neutral with other nations for as long as possible will be central to ensuring Novgorod maintains its position as the wealthiest city in the region.\n\nNovgorod must establish a power base in its mighty capital through trade and strong defences to have a chance of success. Its large populations and loyal, experienced citizen army will ensure a strong local militia to defend its cities. With strong armies of local militia and limitless trade opportunities, Novgorod truly is a “Sleeping Giant” that will have the ability to march on any nation when it chooses to awaken.\n\nAlthough Novgorod has a fierce citizen army, it is their Boyar Sons that are the pride of the nation. Novgorod must use the expendable local militia to ensure the Boyar Sons are not wasted on the front line. These warriors are second to none with a javelin, and with a sword or axe in hand they can match even the best. On the open plains, there is no more devastating a sight than an army of Boyar Sons riding with javelin in hand and all manner of armour and weapons glistening in the sun.
{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_NOVGOROD_TITLE}Republic of Novgorod
{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_SCOTLAND_DESCR}Difficulty: Estimated Medium \n\nWith seemingly more Norwegian forces arriving on his northern doorstep every day and a precarious relationship with the power hungry English to the south, the Scottish King currently finds himself in a tenuous situation. The Norwegian Vikings seem to have a single-minded determination to conquer Scotland. However, They only have a small foothold in the northern Highlands, and Norway is a very long distance away. Re-inforcements for these Norse raiders will be hard to come by, and the Scottish people will happily try to see these invaders out of their homeland.\n\n The way to deal with England, however, is far from clear. It would seem England’s desire to conquer Ireland and control Wales has spread their armies thinly about the Isle, therefore if the chance to re-capture former Scottish territories to the south should arise, the king must be alive to the opportunity. If England should manage to pacify Ireland and Wales, their ambition will naturally carry them into Scottish territory, and by that point they will be too powerful to keep in check.\n\nScotland will also need to consider their diplomatic options when dealing with the Norwegian and English peoples, as it would be unfortunate and potentially fatal for Scotland to become involved in wars on two fronts.  As an alternative, an early, pre-emptive invasion of Ireland or Wales may give Scotland the upper hand they need to press on and deal the powerful English a severe blow in the future. Their mastery of pike units, as well as utilizing the brave and fierce Highlanders, will also prove to be a powerful strength in time.
{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_SCOTLAND_TITLE}Kingdom of Scotland
{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_SICILY_DESCR}Difficulty: Estimated Medium \n\nAlthough Sicily's proximity to Rome has given the island a rich history, it now stands as a relative fledgling among the European powers. The island has been under the governorship of the Norman de Hauteville dynasty for over a century. These Normans came to the Saracen-controlled island in a spirit of adventure and crusade, to liberate the heartland of Christendom not only from the Saracens, but also from the heretical Orthodox Byzantines in Naples. The Catholic Normans found themselves as the new lords of a multicultural and multi-religious realm, and they have been relatively successful in maintaining an air of religious toleration, even though they have actively promoted Catholic missionary and settlement activities, with increasing success. \n\nEver the seafaring adventurers, Sicilian Normans played a large role in the early Crusades. The current Prince of Antioch, Bohemund III, is a Norman himself, and they are found in large numbers across the Crusader States. Sicily has used the Crusades to begin the construction of a robust navy to ferry troops not only to Outremer, but also to other lands in the Mediterranean where the Normans can extend their holdings. \n\nThe Sicilians own more land in Italy than any other faction, but the peninsula provides both probems and opportunities for them. The sheer presence of Papal Rome midway along the Italian Peninsula now serves as a sturdy political shield from the continental powers to the north. It's a barrier that looks likely to hold so long as the Catholic lords all remain faithful to the Papacy. Hiding behind a shield is however, not the way to establish an empire - nor is any defence without its weakness. If the Sicilians successfully start to expand up the peninsula, they will soon have to deal with the Holy Roman Empire, the Milanese and the Venetians.\n\nIt would seem that the Normans will once again have to take to the waters to expand their kingdom. Close to home, other islands like Sardinia and Malta make tempting targets for invasion. However, the Sicilians will need to look over the horizon to have a hope of long term survival. To the east, the Byzantine Empire is strong and unified, but it is starting to buckle under heavy attacks from the Seljuk Turks, and will pay their westernmost provinces little mind until a Sicilian attack. There is also ample opportunity to take advantage of the chaos on the Iberian Peninsula to the west, or even coming to the aid of their crusading brethren in the Holy Land by launching an invasion of Islamic Egypt.
{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_SICILY_TITLE}Kingdom of Sicily
{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_SPAIN_DESCR}Difficulty: Estimated Medium \n\nKing Alfonso IX of Leon and Castile has shown himself to be a powerful and astute ruler of the largest and most powerful of the Iberian Christian kingdoms. The capture of Toledo in 1085 had allowed the people of Leon and Castile to re-establish themselves as a culture (with a little help from recovered Arabic manuals in Toledo), and the crusades in the Holy Land have only further hardened the Christian Iberian spirit to continue the Reconquista. In emulation of the birth of the Templars and Hospitallers in Palestine, many Spanish crusading orders, most notably the Knights of Santiago, have been formed to lend their swords and faith to driving the Moors back to Africa. \n\nHowever, the threats faced by Castile and Leon are very dire as well. The former Moorish rulers of Andalucia (Islamic Iberia), the Almoravid Caliphs, had grown weak and complacent living in opulent splendor in Cordoba, and could not face a more militant and radical sect of Moors, the Almohads, who rose from Moorish Africa and vigorously supplanted the Almoravids. The Almohads are fanatical jihadists who have none of the refinement or tolerance that the Almoravids displayed, and are trying to roll back the advances made by the Christian kingdoms. The fighting in Iberia will be extremely fierce in the immediate future.\n\nAlfonso would also be wise to ally himself with his "peer", the king of Portugal. While Alfonso may still view Portugal as his feudal property, the new papal proclamation declaring Portugal as a kingdom, and the benefits of concerting the efforts of Iberian Christians in the face of their energetic new enemy will outweight the blow to his pride...at least temporarily. \n\n Once Iberia is reclaimed for Christ, Castile's overland options are limited. Across the Pyranees, the feudal lords of France stand behind their strong king, Philip II Augustus, and will make potent enemies should Castile decide to expand in that direction. Unless the Castilian royalty are willing to embark on such a dangerous campaign, they must look to the sea to find less daunting borders to cross. The Iberians have always shown an affinity for the water, and make fine seafarers. Who knows, perhaps the great empires of the future will be forged at sea rather than on dry land - If so, the people who mastered this art of war first would inherit the earth.
{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_SPAIN_TITLE}Kingdom of Castile
{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_TIMURIDS_DESCR}Difficulty: Estimated Medium \n\nForged in conquest and terror, the Timurid Empire rose from the ashes of the fractured Mongol world. Timur, known in the West as Tamerlane, united the Turkic and Mongol tribes of Transoxiana under his banner, proclaiming himself the rightful heir to Genghis Khan’s legacy. From Samarkand, he unleashed a series of devastating campaigns that would reshape Central Asia, Persia, and the Middle East.\n\nTimur’s armies marched with ruthless efficiency, crushing the Golden Horde, annihilating the armies of Delhi, and laying waste to Persia, Mesopotamia, and Anatolia. Cities that resisted were destroyed, their populations massacred, while those that submitted were spared to fuel further conquest. Though Timur ruled in the name of a puppet Chinggisid khan, real power rested solely in his hands.\n\nAt Timur’s death in 1405, the empire stretched from the Indus River to the Mediterranean frontier, yet its foundations were unstable. His heirs inherited vast lands but faced internal rivalries, rebellious governors, and powerful neighbors eager to reclaim lost territories. To preserve Timur’s legacy, the Timurid rulers must balance conquest with consolidation, or see their empire fracture as swiftly as it was forged.
{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_TIMURIDS_TITLE}The Timurid Empire
{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_TITLE}Grand Campaign
{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_TURKS_DESCR}Difficulty: Estimated Hard \n\nSince migrating from the Steppes the nomadic Seljuk Turks have had an incredible impact on the Middle East. Relying heavily on their swift light cavalry the Seljuk Turks have seized lands in Syria and Asia Minor and settled down to become a major power in the Middle East. However, prior to the First Crusade the Seljuks began to fragment amongst themselves, draining away much of their strength and momentum, ultimately resulting in the unlikely success of the First Crusade and the subsequent founding of the Crusader States. \n\nOwing to the determination and leadership of Nur ad-Din and his immediate predecessor, Zenghi, (Nur ad-Din’s father), the Syrian based Seljuks have begun to effectively challenge the Crusaders. \n\nNur ad-Din sent a very capable lieutenant by the name of Salah al-Din to Egypt to rule it in his name. Unfortunately for Nur ad-Din his former lieutenant had ambitions of his own and soon took Egypt as his own. This betrayal may prove dangerous for Nur ad-Din, as besides being a cunning general, Salah al-Din has revitalised Egypt into a mighty force once again. \n\nIt is almost a given that master and former lieutenant will have to face off against one another if either are to expand. Such a confrontation will drain away forces desperately needed by both parties to drive off the accursed Crusaders. On the other hand the victor of such a clash will gain a large Islamic Empire that the Crusaders will be hard pressed to defend against.
{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_TURKS_TITLE}Seljuk Sultanate
{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_VENICE_DESCR}Difficulty: Estimated Medium \n\nThe city of canals is a reminder that starting from a great defensive position is an ideal foundation upon which to build an empire. With the city itself perched on the Ri'Alto island and the Venetian Lagoon serving as a massive moat for the city, Venice is a natural fortress. Although the Venetians do not boast a noteworthy land army, they are the leading seafarers of the time. This gives them the ability to confidently defend their capital from direct attack, as well as establish trade routes more readily than most any other major power.\n\nThe Crusades have been a major boon for the mercantile and naval Venetians. They have provided close support for the crusaders in the Holy Land, whether serving as a base of resupply or by helping the crusading armies capture important coastal cities like Jaffa and Ascalon. Venetian vessels are also prime vehicles for trade between Christendom and the Holy Land. The Crusader States have begun acquiring a great deal of wealth and luxury items from their new oriental home, and Venice has profited greatly from the rapid increase in trade between the Latin East and the Latin West.\n\nThe proverbial fly in the ointment for the Venetians, however, is the Byzantine Empire. Byzantine merchants not only infringe on Venetian business with the Crusader States on grounds of "feudal obligations" from the First Crusade, but also by directly competing with the Venetian merchants to make sure that the economic fruits of the Crusades go to Constantinople, not Venice. The current Doge of Venice, Dandolo, is now looking for any pretense with which to escalate the Venetian trade war with the Byzantines to a real one.\n\nThe situation in Italy is also an interesting one for Venice. Milan and the Lombard League, which Venice was once a member of, is continuing to fight Emperor Bararossa for control of northern Italy. Venice stands neutral to both at this time. Picking a right moment to strike in this war could allow Venice to take control of the whole region- one of the wealthiest and most defensible realms in Christendom.
{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_VENICE_TITLE}Republic of Venice
{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_WALES_DESCR}Difficulty: Estimated Medium \n\nThe Britons, the original peoples of Roman Brittania (whom can lay claim to the legendary King Arthur, or Artorius in his Latin name) fled westward to the edges of the island before the invasions of the Angles and Saxons in the 5th century AD, and eventually became the Principality of Wales. The Welsh see themselves and their culture as distinct from the English (the descendents of the Anglo-Saxon invaders) in almost every way, shape and form. Excepting, of course, their common bond in Catholic Christianity. \n\nThe Welsh are ruled over by princes of powerful noble houses and localised dynasties whose individual territories criss-cross their little patch of Britannia, but they are ruled over by a High Prince that can direct his people in times of need. \n\nThis is one of those times. \n\nThe English, under King Henry II, are seeking to incorporate Wales into the Kingdom of England through sheer force. The English can muster a far greater number of men and resources than the Welsh, but the soldiers of Wales are strong, motivated, and free. The Welsh have also developed a powerful weapon with which to combat the armored English troops: the longbow. They also can make use of powerful spearmen and heavy infantry to protect their archers.\n\nThe Welsh are all that remain of Roman Britannia, and they will fight to the last man before their proud legacy is snuffed out by the descendents of the very barbarians that their legendary king, Arthur, fought against in days of old.
{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_WALES_TITLE}Wales
{NORMAN_PROLOGUE_NORMANS_DESCR}Lead William the Conqueror and his Norman army to victory at the Battle of Hastings, then defeat the Saxons for control of the English throne. \n\nEdward the Confessor's death saw England fall into a bitter power struggle. With no heirs to the English throne, three competing powers arose to stake their claim. Harold Godwinson was quick to seize power, with the support of the English Witan. However, the King of Norway, Harald Hardrada, felt the land his birthright and sailed from the North. The two kings clashed at Stamford Bridge in a bloody battle.\n\nBut the late King Edward had promised the throne to the Duke of Normandy, who sought Papal blessing to launch an invasion of his own.
{NORMAN_PROLOGUE_NORMANS_TITLE}The Norman Conquest
{NORMAN_PROLOGUE_TITLE}The Norman Conquest

