¬v1.6
{AMERICA_DISCOVERED_BODY}	Testing the theory that one can head east by sailing west carried the risk of a remote, watery grave. Yet this act of courage has been rewarded with the discovery of a strange new land... perchance a whole new world. Who knows what riches await those with the courage to explore.
{AMERICA_DISCOVERED_TITLE}	New World Discovered

{AZTECS_CONTACTED_BODY}	It seems the new world is already dominated by an ancient culture - the Mexìcâs. For a seemingly simple people, their cities are vast and complicated. Their primitive outlook belies their ability to raise vast stone structures that rival anything the old world has to offer. And if gold is the measure of an Empire's might, then the Mexìcâs are formidable indeed.
{AZTECS_CONTACTED_TITLE}	New World Inhabited

{BLACK_DEATH_1_BODY}	The dire plague that scholars have now dubbed "The Great Mortality" is continuing its destructive trail through the west. Is the end truly nigh? Is this our judgement, and has the almighty finally decided that we are all too wretched to live?!
{BLACK_DEATH_1_TITLE}	The Great Mortality

{BLACK_DEATH_2_BODY}	Life in the civilised world has become more morbid and bleak than in known history. Every man woman and child is accustomed to the sight of their people stacked in piles before being burned... In the vain hope that the fires may cleanse this foul doom from the land.

Although not everyone is falling victim to its deadly embrace, the plague is still decimating the population everywhere it travels.
{BLACK_DEATH_2_TITLE}	The Great Mortality Spreads

{BLACK_DEATH_3_BODY}	While the lands that were first stricken by the Great Mortality are beginning to discover a life beyond the plague, many places that had been spared this doom are now feeling its full effects.

Though talk of this truly being the end is becoming less likely with enough survivors to prove the point, this creeping doom is still the most feared thing to stalk the lands of Europe for even the bravest of men, being dubbed "The Black Death" these days.
{BLACK_DEATH_3_TITLE}	The Great Mortality Continues

{BLACK_DEATH_4_BODY}	It would appear that the Black Death has worked most of its deadly misery upon the world, and that men of all faiths may have reason to make a prayer of thanks... We have been delivered!

Aside from some unfortunate destinations at the end of the major trade routes where the plague is a more recent tyrant, the risk of contracting the Black Death appears to now be negligible. Now those who rule the survivors may struggle over what remains of civilisation.
{BLACK_DEATH_4_TITLE}	The Black Death Passes

{BLACK_DEATH_HITS_BODY}	A plague of unfathomable proportions has made its way westward from the Far East, where it is said to have already ended an untold number of lives. The victims find their skin covered in dark blotches, as they enter a terrible fever and sickness which ultimately leads to a painful and miserable death.  While scholars, theologians and physicians cannot agree on the exact cause of this deadly plague, the threat it poses men of all faiths is plain for all to see.
{BLACK_DEATH_HITS_TITLE}	A Most Dreaded Plague

{EARTHQUAKE_IN_ALEPPO_BODY}	The people of Aleppo have suffered terribly, as the very earth beneath the city and surrounding lands buckled and broke in what could only be described as a terrible act of divine wrath or punishment. God willing, the people of Aleppo will soon rebuild their city.
{EARTHQUAKE_IN_ALEPPO_TITLE}	Earthquake in Aleppo!

{EARTHQUAKE_IN_ALEXANDRIA_2_BODY}	Those at Alexandria that lived to remember the last earthquake that ravaged the city have now had to endure this destructive nightmare twice! The people of this city can still take hope in the defiant survival of the Lighthouse, though its now huge wounds are a stark reminder of this place's misfortune.
{EARTHQUAKE_IN_ALEXANDRIA_2_TITLE}	Alexandria Suffers Again!

{EARTHQUAKE_IN_ALEXANDRIA_BODY}	An earthquake has shaken the entire eastern Mediterranean basin, most terribly so at the ancient city of Alexandria. Lives were lost in the ensuing chaos and destruction caused by falling buildings. Even the great Lighthouse that has stood for over a millennia bears scars from the tremendous power of the quake.
{EARTHQUAKE_IN_ALEXANDRIA_TITLE}	Earthquake in Alexandria!

{EARTHQUAKE_IN_NAPLES_BODY}	Sitting in the shadow of Vesuvius, the people of Naples have always known that they have lived with the constant threat of danger. However, the terrible earthquake that has recently brought down countless buildings and ended many lives is probably not the disaster they expected to befall them.
{EARTHQUAKE_IN_NAPLES_TITLE}	Napoli Endures Earthquake!

{EARTHQUAKE_IN_SILICIA_BODY}	A mighty earthquake has struck in the region of Silicia with damage being felt as far as way as Iconium. Fortunately the centre of the destructive power wasn't so close to this major population centre, although the casualties in the region have still been significant.
{EARTHQUAKE_IN_SILICIA_TITLE}	Silicia Suffers Quake!

{FIRST_BLAST_FURNACE_BODY}	A new way of working metal is now being practised in the village of Lapphyttan in Sweden, and adopted in western Europe. Housed in a great building, mighty water-driven bellows blast air into a furnace that produces a blaze so fierce and unworldly that the iron from within the ore flows out as a stream of molten metal!

Even though the raw iron that pours from this new furnace is very brittle, vast amounts of the stuff can be made with relative ease, which a learned smith can then easily treat to produce incredibly resilient weapons and armour.
{FIRST_BLAST_FURNACE_TITLE}	Man-made Inferno!

{FIRST_EUROPEAN_PAPER_BODY}	Word is spreading across Europe on a new medium... Written on pressed paper! What has been an expensive luxury imported from the Middle East and beyond has now come to western Europe.

A small mill devoted to pressing paper into sheets has been established in Xativa, south of Valencia. Although the ongoing Reconquista suggests that Islam is not welcome in Iberia, it is evident that some Muslim culture and innovations definitely are.
{FIRST_EUROPEAN_PAPER_TITLE}	European Paper

{FIRST_EYEGLASSES_BODY}	Reports are coming in from northern Italy of scholars placing delicate glass lenses in a thin metallic frame to be worn on the face. Apparently, if the lenses are made to the correct size they can help those with poor sight to see like normal, healthier citizens. Aesthetes among the scholarly community are concerned that wearing such a contraption will result in being teased or shunned.
{FIRST_EYEGLASSES_TITLE}	Lucid Visions

{FIRST_MAGNETIC_COMPASS_BODY}	It has been discovered that an ore from the Asia Minor region of Magnesia that attracts iron, also can make a piece of that metal orientate itself to point to the north - as reliably as a devout Muslim would turn to face Mecca.  This strange phenomena has been captured in a small device known as a 'compass' that cartographers and navigators have begun embracing in earnest, claiming it will take much of the guess work out of the art of exploration and map making.
{FIRST_MAGNETIC_COMPASS_TITLE}	Scientific Breakthrough

{FIRST_MECHANICAL_CLOCK_BODY}	An elaborate new time-measuring device has begun to appear in several places around Europe that does not rely upon water or the light of the sun to work. Scholars have explained that it has been discovered that the motion of a swinging object can be used to drive the 'clock' mechanism.

Those that have seen one of these new mechanical clocks have suggested making one large enough to see from a distance would be useful.
{FIRST_MECHANICAL_CLOCK_TITLE}	Time Machine Made

{FIRST_OIL_PAINTING_BODY}	A Flemish painter, Jan van Eyck, is now championing an outlandish concept to produce paint created from seed oils rather than using tempera egg yolk. He claims that these 'oil paints' dry much more slowly, allowing the artist to take all the time needed to perfect each stroke and feature of their paintings.

Some of the art establishment have declared that they are unconvinced as to the merits of oil paint, most likely because their specialised skills with tempera are about to become obsolete.
{FIRST_OIL_PAINTING_TITLE}	Pioneer of Paint

{FIRST_PIANO_BODY}	With the Papacy no longer denouncing polyphony, the musical technique where two melodies are united, we are now in an age where aspiring musical artists are pioneering new ways to make heavenly music.

The most recent advent in the musical world is an instrument known as a spinet. A true modern mechanical marvel, the spinet is driven by row of black and white keys, just like a pipe organ, that when pressed strike varying notes on strings cased within. The sounds it produces are not so powerful or profound as the pipe organ, making it something a wealthy noble or merchant could have in their home.
{FIRST_PIANO_TITLE}	Portable Pipe Organ?

{FIRST_PRINTED_BIBLE_BODY}	The same clergymen that were denouncing the printing press have now made a total about face, hailing Gutenburg as a spreader of the faith. The first book Gutenburg's printing company has been commissioned to publish is the Holy Bible itself.

Whether this came about as a result of Gutenburg fearing retribution from the Papacy, or because the Catholic church is one of the few establishments wealthy enough to finance such a project matters little - Bibles will soon be readily accessible to the common man&  Even if he lacks the skills needed to read it.
{FIRST_PRINTED_BIBLE_TITLE}	Papacy Pro-Printing

{FIRST_PRINTING_PRESS_BODY}	News has arrived from Mainz that a goldsmith named Johann Gutenburg has invented a machine capable of repeatedly printing an entire page of the written word. Called the 'printing press', this machine has rows of slots that hold raised letters on tiny metal blocks. So long as the letters are properly arranged into words and sentences, it is then a simple matter of pressing the metallic type onto ink, and then paper to do in moments what takes a scribe considerable time.

There are some members of the cloth already claiming that the mass-production of books may result in widespread literacy, which will in turn lead to the unsupervised consumption of heretical beliefs.
{FIRST_PRINTING_PRESS_TITLE}	The Mechanical Scribe!

{FIRST_PUBLIC_CLOCK_BODY}	The citizens of the city of Milan can now claim to be the most punctual in the known world, or at least, their overseers and taskmasters can claim to know when their workers are tardy. An expensive mechanical clock has been set atop a tower, so that everyone from prince to pauper may see the time displayed from the city streets.

Typically, now that scholars and engineers have succeeded in creating a truly grand mechanical clock, the more malcontent members of the noble class have begun calling for a portable version of the device!
{FIRST_PUBLIC_CLOCK_TITLE}	Time for Everyone

{FIRST_RUDDER_BODY}	Arabic sailors have successfully adopted an old seafaring trick from the Far East, using a plate of wood called a 'rudder' at the rear of a ship to change its path through the water. Some outlandish notions are being raised by some of the more eccentric military strategists that suggest that wars will one day be waged at sea, and that the rudder is a vital step toward their vision being realised.
{FIRST_RUDDER_TITLE}	Seafaring Innovation

{FIRST_SAWMILL_BODY}	Great minds have found new ways to make light of some of the heaviest work. Sawing wood has always been slow work for even the strongest labourers, but cunning engineers have found a way to drive a great saw capable of planing an entire log by using water!
{FIRST_SAWMILL_TITLE}	The Forest is Conquered!

{FIRST_WATCH_BODY}	At last an inventor has found a means to create a portable timepiece! Peter Henlein, a locksmith from Nuremberg has created a small clock being dubbed the 'Nuremberg Egg' for its oval shape. Once its spring mechanism inside its shell is wound, the 'egg' will display the hour, for almost two full days.

Despite still being large enough to leave an incredibly unseemly lump in one's pocket, being seen in possession of one of Henlein's Nuremberg Eggs has become 'the' trinket to be seen to possess - for the few that can afford one.
{FIRST_WATCH_TITLE}	Portable Clock

{FIRST_WHEELBARROW_BODY}	Tales of a clever invention from the Far East have recently inspired European peasants to come up with a simple labourer's aid they are referring to as the 'wheelbarrow' .

By placing a wheel at the front of a wooden stretcher, it has been discovered that a lone worker can move a heavy load of stone on their own, with little risk of injury. It could be as much of a boon for lords seeking to raise castles in quick time, as it will be for the serfs who shall have to build them.
{FIRST_WHEELBARROW_TITLE}	A Boon for Builders

{FIRST_WINDMILL_BODY}	Reports are coming in from across Western Europe of engineers who have created a miracle mill that requires no stream or river to power it. Supposedly, man has found a way to let the very winds themselves drive massive mill mechanisms, simply by catching it in sails on beams of wood. While the Windmill's effectiveness reportedly dies as the winds do, to those living far from running water, it is sure to be considered a Godsend.
{FIRST_WINDMILL_TITLE}	Making the Wind Work

{FOOTBALL_BANNED_BODY}	The Lord Mayor of London has issued a proclamation of the banning of some violent mob behaviour that the commoners seen enamoured with...

"And whereas there is a great uproar in the City through certain tumults arising from the striking of great footballs in the field of the public - from which many evils perchance may arise - which may God forbid - we do command and do forbid, on the King's behalf, upon pain of imprisonment, that such games shall not be practised henceforth within this city."

Now that this law has been passed, the establishment are confident that these 'football' events have no chance of becoming an obsession of religious proportions.
{FOOTBALL_BANNED_TITLE}	Football Denounced

{GROTE_MANDENKE_BODY}	An incredible south-westerly Atlantic gale like never seen before has struck the north-western tip of Europe, lashing England, right across to Denmark. Unstoppable storm tides have swept inland, killing many, and conditions at sea are dire enough to make sailing for the brave and foolish only.
{GROTE_MANDENKE_TITLE}	The Great Drowning of Men

{GUNPOWDER_DISCOVERED_BODY}	A new discovery that could change the course of warfare - Gunpowder. This dark powder may look innocent enough, but when brought to spark it explodes with a force that is unmatched.
This terrible weapon will make armour obsolete, and render castle walls near useless. It would be wise to be the first to master its use in war.
{GUNPOWDER_DISCOVERED_TITLE}	A Deadly New Weapon!

{HANSEATIC_BUILT_DENMARK_BODY}Our informants have reported rumours that the Hanseatic League has constructed their headquarters in one of our rival's cities close to the Baltic Sea. This structure effectively allows them to control most of the trade agreements in the Baltic region, resulting in a substantial increase in trade income for all their settlements.  It would be wise of us to deprive them of this powerful resource as soon as possible, either via sabotage or outright conquest of the city!
{HANSEATIC_BUILT_DENMARK_TITLE}Hanseatic League Headquarters

{HANSEATIC_BUILT_RUSSIA_BODY}Our informants have reported rumours that the Hanseatic League has constructed their headquarters in one of our rival's cities close to the Baltic Sea. This structure effectively allows them to control most of the trade agreements in the Baltic region, resulting in a substantial increase in trade income for all their settlements.  It would be wise of us to deprive them of this powerful resource as soon as possible, either via sabotage or outright conquest of the city!
{HANSEATIC_BUILT_RUSSIA_TITLE}Hanseatic League Headquarters

{HANSEATIC_BUILT_NOVGOROD_BODY}Our informants have reported rumours that the Hanseatic League has constructed their headquarters in one of our rival's cities close to the Baltic Sea. This structure effectively allows them to control most of the trade agreements in the Baltic region, resulting in a substantial increase in trade income for all their settlements.  It would be wise of us to deprive them of this powerful resource as soon as possible, either via sabotage or outright conquest of the city!
{HANSEATIC_BUILT_NOVGOROD_TITLE}Hanseatic League Headquarters

{HANSEATIC_BUILT_LITHUANIA_BODY}Our informants have reported rumours that the Hanseatic League has constructed their headquarters in one of our rival's cities close to the Baltic Sea. This structure effectively allows them to control most of the trade agreements in the Baltic region, resulting in a substantial increase in trade income for all their settlements.  It would be wise of us to deprive them of this powerful resource as soon as possible, either via sabotage or outright conquest of the city!
{HANSEATIC_BUILT_LITHUANIA_TITLE}Hanseatic League Headquarters

{HANSEATIC_BUILT_NORWAY_BODY}Our informants have reported rumours that the Hanseatic League has constructed their headquarters in one of our rival's cities close to the Baltic Sea. This structure effectively allows them to control most of the trade agreements in the Baltic region, resulting in a substantial increase in trade income for all their settlements.  It would be wise of us to deprive them of this powerful resource as soon as possible, either via sabotage or outright conquest of the city!
{HANSEATIC_BUILT_NORWAY_TITLE}Hanseatic League Headquarters

{HANSEATIC_BUILT_POLAND_BODY}Our informants have reported rumours that the Hanseatic League has constructed their headquarters in one of our rival's cities close to the Baltic Sea. This structure effectively allows them to control most of the trade agreements in the Baltic region, resulting in a substantial increase in trade income for all their settlements.  It would be wise of us to deprive them of this powerful resource as soon as possible, either via sabotage or outright conquest of the city!
{HANSEATIC_BUILT_POLAND_TITLE}Hanseatic League Headquarters

{HANSEATIC_BUILT_TEUTONIC_BODY}Our informants have reported rumours that the Hanseatic League has constructed their headquarters in one of our rival's cities close to the Baltic Sea. This structure effectively allows them to control most of the trade agreements in the Baltic region, resulting in a substantial increase in trade income for all their settlements.  It would be wise of us to deprive them of this powerful resource as soon as possible, either via sabotage or outright conquest of the city!
{HANSEATIC_BUILT_TEUTONIC_TITLE}Hanseatic League Headquarters

{HANSEATIC_DESTROYED_BODY}Whether by an act of fate or deliberate intent the Hanseatic League Headquarters no longer stands!  We must take the initiative and look to control the key trading cities of Riga, Visby, Novgorod, Danzig and Hamburg in the hopes of attracting the League to rebuild their headquarters in one of our towns.
{HANSEATIC_DESTROYED_TITLE}Hanseatic League Sabotaged?

{HANSEATIC_FORMATION_BODY}Reports have been received from our traders that the Merchants’ Guilds in the cities of Riga, Visby, Novgorod, Danzig and Hamburg have formed an alliance known as the Hanseatic League.  We would do well to ensure that we bring these key trading cities under our control quickly, in the hope that this new League will present us with the opportunity to construct, and therefore control, their headquarters.
{HANSEATIC_FORMATION_TITLE}Hanseatic League Grows

{LITHUANIA_CONVERSION_BODY}As the roots of the Roman Catholic Church spread throughout Europe, a number of our nobles are now suggesting that Lithuania should look to complete the actions of Midigaus, the first Grand Duke and founder of the Lithuanian state, and have our people convert to the Catholic faith.  While this decision may provoke the ire of those Lithuanians who are entrenched in their Pagan ways, the benefits of converting include access to the advanced knowledge of other Catholic nations and a greater chance of securing robust alliances with neighbours who share our faith.  With this in mind, would you like to have the people of Lithuania convert to Catholicism?
{LITHUANIA_CONVERSION_TITLE}A New Faith for a New Era

{LITHUANIA_CONVERTS_BODY}Christendom rejoices! The mother Church has gained a new sheep to the fold. The people of Lithuania have agreed to put aside their Pagan ways and embrace the Holy Word of Christ.
{LITHUANIA_CONVERTS_TITLE}A Catholic Lithuania

{MALLEUS_MALEFICARUM_BODY}	In these dark times that see the Lord's children under constant exposure to heresy, and in extreme cases, witchcraft, at last we have been armed with the knowledge to drive back and defeat the forces of darkness - the Malleus Maleficarum, meaning, "The Hammer of Witches".  This tome has immediately been accepted as the definitive instruction set for a trial of heresy, covering everything from detecting witchcraft through to how to forcibly purge a human vessel of sin.
{MALLEUS_MALEFICARUM_TITLE}	The Hammer of Witches'

{TEUTONIC_ORDER_VOLUNTEERS_BODY}	Word arrives that the famed knight, Tancred von Luxemburg, has landed in Courland with a retinue of seasoned warriors. A veteran of the crusades in the Holy Land and a devout servant of the Church, his arrival is a potent boost to morale and military strength in the campaign against the pagans.
{TEUTONIC_ORDER_VOLUNTEERS_TITLE}	Baltic Crusade

{TEUTONIC_ORDER_SCANDINAVIA_BODY}	The Grand Master's strategic vision reaches across the sea! A detachment of our finest Teutonic Knights, under the command of the experienced Marshal Hugo of Nassau, has successfully landed on the Scandinavian coast. Their mission is to prosecute the Holy War against the pagan tribes in the North, opening a new front and securing crucial northern territories for the Order and for Christendom.
{TEUTONIC_ORDER_SCANDINAVIA_TITLE}	Swedish Crusade

{LITHUANIANS_ARISE_BODY} The arrival of a great Frankish army under Tancred von Luxemburg has not broken the spirit of the Lithuanian people, but ignited it! Fear of the cross and foreign domination has sparked a fierce resistance. The baltic tribes have rallied under the banner of Preigilas of Siauliai, a hero who vows to drive the crusading invaders and the cursed Order back into the sea. Survival demands a fight!	
{LITHUANIANS_ARISE_TITLE}	Defender of the Romuva 

{SCIENCE_ALCHEMY_BOOK_BODY}	Robert of Chester, an English translator has completed his transcription of the Liber de Compositione Alchemiae, or more simply, the Book of the Composition of Alchemy. Originally an Arabic text, this grand compendium of scientific and alchemical discoveries and musings is being deemed an affront to holy mandate by the establishment... But rumour has it most scholars would risk being associated with heretical beliefs to glean the knowledge hidden within its pages.
{SCIENCE_ALCHEMY_BOOK_TITLE}	Liber de Compositione Alchemiae

{SCIENCE_DA_VINCI_ORNITHOPTER_BODY}	Leonardo da Vinci, an Italian mastermind known for his revolutionary artistic works and ingenious inventions has concocted his most ambitious and eldritch design yet. His fascination with the science of flight has culminated in his 'Ornithopter' design.  Looking something akin to a windmill sail atop a horseless carriage, many other scholars are laughing, suggesting da Vinci should go back to his concepts based upon attaching wings to the human body.
{SCIENCE_DA_VINCI_ORNITHOPTER_TITLE}	Machines that Fly?

{SCIENCE_DE_DOCTA_IGNORANTIA_BODY}	A Catholic scholar, Nicholas of Cusa has published a series of scientific and philosophical claims, bundled together under the somewhat arrogant title of De Docta Ignorantia - literally meaning, 'Of Learned Ignorance' .

His theories include the notion that the Earth is not the centre of the Universe, and that it actually orbits the Sun. Even more fantastical, he even attests that the stars of the night sky are actually distant suns themselves!
{SCIENCE_DE_DOCTA_IGNORANTIA_TITLE}	Of Learned Ignorance

{SCIENCE_MATHS_ZERO_EUROPE_BODY}	A mathematician from Pisa by the name of Fibonacci has published a new work entitled 'Liber Abaci'. He has adopted some Hindu-Arabic theories involving a number that has no value, claiming this is a vital step for making calculations on a grand scale.  Despite managing to excite western scholars, the Liber Abaci's revelations offer few insights to the common man... who typically spends all his life dealing with things of 'no value'.
{SCIENCE_MATHS_ZERO_EUROPE_TITLE}	The Hero of Zero

{SCIENCE_WEATHER_FORECAST_BODY}	An aspiring English scholar by the name of Walter Merle claims that he is able to predict the weather - unlike the mystical ramblings of yesteryear's heretical pagans who claimed to have a spiritual insight into when the heavens will open up, Merle has stated he can do this simply by scientific observation.

Apparently Merle's predictions are correct more often than not, but his system is still being perfected. Surely it will only be a matter of months now before man knows exactly how the weather will behave.
{SCIENCE_WEATHER_FORECAST_TITLE}	Bold Predictions

{KIEV_SACKED_BODY}The Mongols attacked Russia, where they made great havoc, destroying cities and fortresses and slaughtering men; and they laid siege to Kiev, the capital of Russia; after they had besieged the city for a long time, they took it and put the inhabitants to death. Kiev had been a very large and thickly populated town, but now it has been reduced almost to nothing, for there are at the present time scarce two hundred houses there and the inhabitants are kept in complete slavery.  
{KIEV_SACKED_TITLE}Mongols Sack Kiev

{WORLD_IS_ROUND_BODY}	Over the centuries several scholars have suggested that the world could be round, but most of them were burned at the stake as heretics, so the theory hasn't been particularly popular. However, with new advances in the fields of Astronomy, enough of the learned men of the world have accepted that the theory is well worth testing... Perhaps if someone were to establish a trade route to the far east by sailing west, they would both bring the debate to a close, as well as establish a trade lane that is most lucrative.
{WORLD_IS_ROUND_TITLE}	The World is Round

{PLAYER_FIRST_GREAT_JAMA_BODY}The Muslims do not worship symbols, for the prophet, blessed be his name, had decreed that to represent the divine with an icon or image is blasphemy in the extreme. However, nobody could really deny that the sight of this grand mosque serves as a shining example of the might and wisdom of Islam.
{PLAYER_FIRST_GREAT_JAMA_TITLE}First Great Jama

{PLAYER_FIRST_HUGE_CATHEDRAL_BODY}If there were any lingering doubts as to the power of the church, they were dispelled once the people gazed upon God’s greatest house on earth. Its towering presence here shall ensure Christian dominance throughout the land.
{PLAYER_FIRST_HUGE_CATHEDRAL_TITLE}Worlds First Huge Cathedral

{JERUSALEM_ANTIOCH_BODY}By the Grace of God, those who went forth in the name our Lord have captured Jerusalem. Thus the Holy city has been triumphantly reclaimed in the name of Christ. All of Christendom will rejoice, for God's Children may now find salvation in the Kingdom of Heaven. \n\nThe great armies of Antioch have captured Jerusalem!
{JERUSALEM_ANTIOCH_TITLE}Jerusalem Captured

{JERUSALEM_JERUSALEM_BODY}By the Grace of God, those who went forth in the name our Lord have captured Jerusalem. Thus the Holy city has been triumphantly reclaimed in the name of Christ. All of Christendom will rejoice, for God's Children may now find salvation in the Kingdom of Heaven. \n\nThe noble armies of Jerusalem's Kingdom have recaptured the Holy City!
{JERUSALEM_JERUSALEM_TITLE}Jerusalem Captured

{JERUSALEM_EGYPT_BODY}Today the followers of the Prophet Mohammed rejoice. For Muslim armies have captured the Holy city of Jerusalem. \n\nEgypt's triumphant armies have captured Jerusalem!
{JERUSALEM_EGYPT_TITLE}Jerusalem Captured

{JERUSALEM_TURKS_BODY}Today the followers of the Prophet Mohammed rejoice. For Muslim armies have captured the Holy city of Jerusalem. \n\nThe mighty Turks  have captured Jerusalem!
{JERUSALEM_TURKS_TITLE}Jerusalem Captured

{MOORS_KING_EVENT_BODY}With the death of the late Moorish ruler, his heir has succeeded to the throne. The Royal Houses know not whether to find fear or comfort in this knowledge...
{MOORS_KING_EVENT_TITLE}The Moorish Sultan is dead!

{PORTUGAL_KING_EVENT_BODY}With the death of the late King of Portugal, his heir has succeeded to the throne. The Royal Houses know not whether to find fear or comfort in this knowledge...
{PORTUGAL_KING_EVENT_TITLE}The King of Portugal is dead!

{SPAIN_KING_EVENT_BODY}With the death of the late King of Spain, his heir has succeeded to the throne. The Royal Houses know not whether to find fear or comfort in this knowledge...
{SPAIN_KING_EVENT_TITLE}The King of Spain is dead!

{EGYPT_KING_EVENT_BODY}With the death of the late Fatimid ruler, his heir has succeeded to the throne. The Royal Houses know not whether to find fear or comfort in this knowledge...
{EGYPT_KING_EVENT_TITLE}The Sultan of Egypt is dead!

{TURKS_KING_EVENT_BODY}With the death of the late Seljuk ruler, his heir has succeeded to the throne. The Royal Houses know not whether to find fear or comfort in this knowledge...
{TURKS_KING_EVENT_TITLE}The Seljuk Sultan is dead!

{BYZANTIUM_KING_EVENT_BODY}With the death of the late Byzantine ruler, his heir has succeeded to the throne. The Royal Houses know not whether to find fear or comfort in this knowledge...
{BYZANTIUM_KING_EVENT_TITLE}The Byzantine Emperor is dead!

{RUSSIA_KING_EVENT_BODY}With the death of the late Kievan Rus ruler, his heir has succeeded to the throne. The Royal Houses know not whether to find fear or comfort in this knowledge...
{RUSSIA_KING_EVENT_TITLE}The King of Kiev is dead!

{NOVGOROD_KING_EVENT_BODY}With the death of the late King of Novgorod, his heir has succeeded to the throne. The Royal Houses know not whether to find fear or comfort in this knowledge...
{NOVGOROD_KING_EVENT_TITLE}The King of Novgorod is dead!

{POLAND_KING_EVENT_BODY}With the death of the late Polish ruler, his heir has succeeded to the throne. The Royal Houses know not whether to find fear or comfort in this knowledge...
{POLAND_KING_EVENT_TITLE}The Polish Duke is dead!

{HUNGARY_KING_EVENT_BODY}With the death of the late Hungarian ruler, his heir has succeeded to the throne. The Royal Houses know not whether to find fear or comfort in this knowledge...
{HUNGARY_KING_EVENT_TITLE}The King of Hungary is dead!

{HRE_KING_EVENT_BODY}With the death of the late German ruler, his heir has succeeded to the throne. The Royal Houses know not whether to find fear or comfort in this knowledge...
{HRE_KING_EVENT_TITLE}The Holy Roman Emperor dies!

{FRANCE_KING_EVENT_BODY}With the death of the late French ruler, his heir has succeeded to the throne. The Royal Houses know not whether to find fear or comfort in this knowledge...
{FRANCE_KING_EVENT_TITLE}The King of France is dead!

{ENGLAND_KING_EVENT_BODY}With the death of the late English ruler, his heir has succeeded to the throne. The Royal Houses know not whether to find fear or comfort in this knowledge...
{ENGLAND_KING_EVENT_TITLE}The King of England is dead!

{SCOTLAND_KING_EVENT_BODY}With the death of the late Scottish ruler, his heir has succeeded to the throne. The Royal Houses know not whether to find fear or comfort in this knowledge...
{SCOTLAND_KING_EVENT_TITLE}The King of Scotland is dead!

{VENICE_KING_EVENT_BODY}With the death of the late Venetian ruler, his heir has succeeded to the throne. The Royal Houses know not whether to find fear or comfort in this knowledge...
{VENICE_KING_EVENT_TITLE}The Vènetian Doge is dead!

{MILAN_KING_EVENT_BODY}With the death of the late Milanese ruler, his heir has succeeded to the throne. The Royal Houses know not whether to find fear or comfort in this knowledge...
{MILAN_KING_EVENT_TITLE}The King of Milan is dead!

{SICILY_KING_EVENT_BODY}With the death of the late Sicilian ruler, his heir has succeeded to the throne. The Royal Houses know not whether to find fear or comfort in this knowledge...
{SICILY_KING_EVENT_TITLE}The King of Sicily is dead!

{DENMARK_KING_EVENT_BODY}With the death of the late Danish ruler, his heir has succeeded to the throne. The Royal Houses know not whether to find fear or comfort in this knowledge...
{DENMARK_KING_EVENT_TITLE}The King of Denmark is dead!

{IRELAND_KING_EVENT_BODY}With the death of the late Irish king, his heir has succeeded to the throne. The Royal Houses know not whether to find fear or comfort in this knowledge...
{IRELAND_KING_EVENT_TITLE}The King of Ireland is dead!

{WALES_KING_EVENT_BODY}With the death of the late Welsh king, his heir has succeeded to the throne. The Royal Houses know not whether to find fear or comfort in this knowledge...
{WALES_KING_EVENT_TITLE}The King of Wales is dead!

{ANTIOCH_KING_EVENT_BODY}With the death of the late King of Antioch, his heir has succeeded to the throne. The Royal Houses know not whether to find fear or comfort in this knowledge...
{ANTIOCH_KING_EVENT_TITLE}The King of Antioch is dead!

{JERUSALEM_KING_EVENT_BODY}With the death of the late King of Jerusalem, his heir has succeeded to the throne. The Royal Houses know not whether to find fear or comfort in this knowledge...
{JERUSALEM_KING_EVENT_TITLE}The King of Jerusalem is dead!

{TEUTONIC_ORDER_KING_EVENT_BODY}With the death of the late Teutonic Order ruler, his heir has succeeded to the throne. The Royal Houses know not whether to find fear or comfort in this knowledge...
{TEUTONIC_ORDER_KING_EVENT_TITLE}The Hochmeister of Teutonic Order is dead!

{LITHUANIA_KING_EVENT_BODY}With the death of the pagan King, his heir has succeeded to the throne. The Royal Houses know not whether to find fear or comfort in this knowledge...
{LITHUANIA_KING_EVENT_TITLE}The King of Lithuania is dead!

{NORWAY_KING_EVENT_BODY}With the death of the late Viking ruler, his heir has succeeded to the throne. The Royal Houses know not whether to find fear or comfort in this knowledge...
{NORWAY_KING_EVENT_TITLE}The King of Norway is dead!

{MONGOLS_KING_EVENT_BODY}With the death of the Great Khan, his heir has succeeded to the throne. The Royal Houses know not whether to find fear or comfort in this knowledge...
{MONGOLS_KING_EVENT_TITLE}Mongolian Khan dies!

{PRINCESS_LOCAL_BODY}This lady of the court is now of age, and thus, a potential bride. Parade her about Europe to meet your political ends, or see that she is wed to woo over your allies. She will not protest, m'lord.
{PRINCESS_LOCAL_TITLE}A Princess Comes of Age!

{EUROPEAN_AID_BODY}Faced with the terrifying prospect of the Mongol Hordes spilling over the Carpathian Mountains and into Central Europe, several Western powers have realized the gravity of the threat. The fall of the Kievan Rus principalities would leave the Polish, Hungarian, and German lands entirely exposed. Driven by a mix of fear and religious fervor, two substantial crusading armies, drawn from the strongest realms of the West, have been dispatched to bolster the defenses of the Rus. A force made up of Polish and German forces have arrived on the western marches, another has arrived by sea at Odessa made up of Italians, Greeks and French soldiers.
{EUROPEAN_AID_TITLE}European Aid to the Kievan Rus

{CUMANS_ARRIVAL_BODY}Driven from their ancestral homes by the iron fist of the Mongol hordes, the fierce Cuman tribes have crossed the Dnieper River in great numbers. These seasoned horse archers and tribal warriors have established a new, formidable presence in the rich lands of Wallachia and the lower Danube region. Settled factions will find it exceedingly difficult to dislodge these highly mobile and aggressive newcomers. However, the Cumans are also pragmatic. They could be convinced—for a hefty price—to lend their unmatched cavalry to a local power in exchange for land, gold, or sanctuary.
{CUMANS_ARRIVAL_TITLE}Cuman Tribes on the move

{OWAIN_GLINDIR_BODY}The long-simmering discontent against foreign occupation has finally boiled over. The charismatic noble, Owain Glyndŵr, claiming descent from the ancient Princes of Wales, has raised his standard in opposition. A hero to his people, he has successfully rallied the Welsh to his cause, promising the restoration of the Welsh Crown. The ensuing revolt has seized castles, disrupted governance, and established a functioning Welsh Parliament. The occupiers now face a grave threat to their dominion over the Marches, and the dream of a free Wales is rekindled in the hearts of every patriot.
{OWAIN_GLINDIR_TITLE}The Glyndwr Rebellion

{TIMURID_REINFORCEMENTS_BODY}The Lion of Samarkand, Amir Timur, and his prodigious son, Bodonchar, have successfully seized Baghdad from the weakened Aq Qoyunlu, securing a vital foothold in the west. Gazing upon the riches and strategic value of the Fertile Crescent, Timur now considers the entire region ripe for conquest. To crush all resistance and cement their authority, swift action is required. Messengers have been dispatched to the eastern provinces, demanding immediate and substantial levies to support the coming great campaign. The armies of the steppe are mustering.
{TIMURID_REINFORCEMENTS_TITLE}Timur on the Warpath

{MONGOL_REINFORCEMENTS_BODY}The Great Khan, Genghis, having firmly secured his dominion over the rich lands of the East, now turns his formidable gaze westward. The vast, fragmented principalities of the Russian steppe and the rich kingdoms of Europe are seen as ripe for subjugation. To guarantee the success of this monumental campaign, the Khan has issued a universal decree, drawing additional hordes from the Asian heartland. The ground trembles as countless horsemen begin their seemingly unstoppable trek towards the setting sun.
{MONGOL_REINFORCEMENTS_TITLE}Mongol Warpath

{WILLIAM_WALLACE_BODY}William Wallace, rising as a symbol of defiance against oppression, has rallied the fierce clans of the Highlands. Hardened by the rugged glens of northern Scotland, these warriors now march under his banner. Their arrival brings renewed strength to the realm, as Scotland braces against those who would see her freedom extinguished.
{WILLIAM_WALLACE_TITLE}William Wallace

{SPANISH_CRUSADE_BODY}Rodrigo of Santiago, guided by fervent devotion and a legacy of valor, has summoned a host from the towns and strongholds of northern Spain. United under his command, this force sets its sights upon the Moorish frontier, determined to reclaim the lands that have long awaited liberation.
{SPANISH_CRUSADE_TITLE}Knights of Santiago

{PORTUGUESE_CRUSADE_BODY}Theodosio of Santiago has forged a steadfast host to safeguard Portugal in her hour of need. Knights, soldiers, and loyal levies gather beneath his standard, prepared to meet any foe that threatens the kingdom’s borders. Their arrival marks a turning point in the defense of Portuguese sovereignty.
{PORTUGUESE_CRUSADE_TITLE}Knights of Santiago

{JERUSALEM_CRUSADE_BODY}Balian of Ibelin, having journeyed through the courts and countryside of Europe, has stirred both noble and commoner to action. Inspired by his cause, they sail with him to the Holy Land. Now disembarked on its shores, this assembled host stands ready to defend Jerusalem against all encroaching powers.
{JERUSALEM_CRUSADE_TITLE}A Host Arrives for Jerusalem

{ANTIOCH_CRUSADE_BODY}Lancelot Longsword, an English knight who has adopted the ancient legends of Arthur as his ideal, has gathered followers from across the Christian world. With his company now landed at Antioch, he pledges his sword to the struggles of Outremer, seeking honor upon the contested frontier of Christendom.
{ANTIOCH_CRUSADE_TITLE}A Knight of Legend Reaches Antioch

{MAMELUKES_ARISE_BODY}Baybars, chief among the Mamelukes, has united the tribes of the desert with his own disciplined warriors. His arrival in the Sinai signals a renewed determination to secure the lands of the Sultan. This formidable host stands prepared to expel foreign powers and restore dominion across the Middle East.
{MAMELUKES_ARISE_TITLE}Mameluke Host Assembles

{NORWEGIAN_EXPANSION_BODY}The king of Norway has dispatched an elite expeditionary force to extend his influence across the North Sea. Veteran warriors and seasoned sailors accompany this host. All that inhabit that region should remain wary.
{NORWEGIAN_EXPANSION_TITLE}A Northern Host Sets Sail

{HUSSITE_REVOLT_BODY}The Hussites have risen in open defiance, casting out their Catholic clergy and establishing a new religious order within their lands. Their doctrines challenge both crown and church, and their sudden ascendancy threatens to unsettle the balance of power. Neighboring realms would be wise to regard this upheaval with caution.
{HUSSITE_REVOLT_TITLE}Hussite Uprising

{WALDENSIAN_REVOLT_BODY}In the valleys of southern France, the Waldensians have cast aside papal authority and armed themselves against perceived tyranny. Their fervent rejection of established doctrine marks them as enemies to most surrounding realms. Travelers and armies alike should advance with care, for these lands now bristle with hostility.
{WALDENSIAN_REVOLT_TITLE}Waldensian Heresy Ignites